## Somil Bansal

Contact

734 Sutardja Dai Hall Berkeley, CA 94720 somilban@usc.edu http://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~somil

AFFILIATION

## University of Southern California

Fall 2021 -

Assistant Professor, Ming Hsieh Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in the intersection of control and dynamical system theory, machine learning, and computer vision for robotic applications.

During my Ph.D., I developed new data-efficient and provably safe learning-based control algorithms for the goal of *safe* and *intelligent* autonomous systems. My approach brings together tools from control theory, machine learning, and computer vision to design systems that possess the ability to learn, improve, and adapt in unknown and dynamic environments in a data-efficient fashion. At the same time, these systems can actively reason about safety and take action to preserve it when necessary. My key research contributions are:

- 1. Data-efficient task-based learning using models and optimal control: developing optimal control-based learning frameworks for efficiently completing a given control task in hard-to-model environments.
- 2. Data-efficient architectures for learning-based perception with model-based control: developing perception-action loops that efficiently combine deep learning-based perception with an underlying dynamics model for control, such as to navigate in *a priori* unknown environments.
- 3. Advancing the theory of optimal control for scalable safety analysis of learning-enabled systems: introducing new formulations and computational tools to enable run-time safety assurance for learning-enabled systems, including large-scale multi-agents systems.
- 4. Safety assurance for learning-enabled systems in unknown and human-centric environments: using the above tools to construct safety envelopes around learning-based perception and human motion prediction components, allowing robust motion plans to avoid collisions with obstacles and humans.

EDUCATION

#### University of California, Berkeley

2015 - 2020

Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences

Advisor: Claire Tomlin

CGPA : 4.0/4.0

#### University of California, Berkeley

2012 - 2014

MS in Electrical Engineering Advisor: Claire Tomlin

CGPA : 4.0/4.0

## Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur

2008 - 2012

B. Tech. in Electrical Engineering

CGPA : 9.8/10

Work Experience

## Waymo, Mountain View

September 2020 - Present

PERIENCE Research Scientist

#### Skydio, Redwood City

May 2018 - Aug 2018

Computer Vision and Planning Intern

Developed and experimentally evaluated algorithms that combine machine learning and planning for autonomous drone navigation in *a priori* unknown environments.

#### Applied Predictive Technologies, San Francisco

Aug 2014 - Sep 2015

Business Consultant

Led data-driven analyses to design business initiatives/promotions and to forecast their performance.

### Broadcom, Sunnyvale

Summer 2013

Performance Engineering Intern

Conducted quantitative analyses to identify performance bottlenecks in existing products.

## University of Western Ontario, London, Canada

Summer 2011

Research Intern

Proposed a novel approach for vector-fitting in the presence of noise for high-frequency applications.

Awards & Honors

#### Eli Jury Award

Department of EECS, UC Berkeley, 2020

"For outstanding achievement in the area of systems, communications, control, or signal processing."

#### Selected for **RSS Pioneers**

RSS, 2019

"A workshop to bring together a cohort of the world's top early career researchers in robotics."

### **Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award**

UC Berkeley, 2019

Awarded to up to 10% of current teaching assistants throughout the university.

#### **Graduate Student Gold Fellowship**

Department of EECS, UC Berkeley, 2013

#### **Excellence Award in Community Services**

IIT Kanpur, 2012

"Recognizing the graduating student with outstanding work in various aspected of community services."

#### Academic Excellence Award (Dean's List)

IIT Kanpur, 2010, 2011.

#### MITACS Globalink Fellowship

IIT Kanpur, 2011

For undergraduate research at University of Western Ontario, London, Canada.

## **Amit Saxena Memorial Award**

IIT Kanpur, 2011

Awarded to the UG student of EE department having the highest score in the courses related to electronics circuits.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### **EE221A: Linear System Theory**

UC Berkeley, Fall 2016, 2018

Graduate Student Instructor

Received the Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor Award.

MTH101: Introduction to Real Analysis and Calculus

IIT Kanpur, Fall 2009, 2010

Academic Mentor

MTH102: Basics of Complex Analysis and Linear Algebra HT Kanpur, Spring 2010, 2011 Academic Mentor

Leadership & Service

#### Workshop Organizer

RSS 2019, 2020: Robust Autonomy: Safe Robot Learning and Control in Uncertain Real-World Environments.

## **Tutorial Organizer**

CDC 2017: Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability: A Brief Overview and Recent Advances. UC Berkeley 2016: Introduction to Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability.

#### **DREAM Seminar Organizer**

2017-2019

Design of Robotics and Embedded systems, Analysis, and Modeling Seminar (DREAMS)

#### **External Reviewer for Conferences and Journals**

Control Theory: CDC 2015-19, ACC 2015-19, HSCC 2019, ICCPS 2019, L-CSS 2018, TAC 2017-19

Machine Learning and Robotics: CoRL 2017-19, IROS 2018-19, ICRA 2018-19, RSS 2019, JMLR 2018, RA-L 2018-19, T-RO 2018-19

#### **Program Committee**

HSCC 2020

#### RESEARCH MENTORSHIP

#### **Masters Students**

- Varun Tolani (UC Berkeley EECS, MSc, 2018), Research assistant at UC Berkeley.
- Anjian Li (Simon Fraser University CS, MSc, 2019).
- Ted Xiao (UC Berkeley EECS, MSc, 2017), Researcher at Google Brain.

#### **Undergraduate Students**

- Khalil Sarwari (UC Berkeley EECS Undergraduate, 2019).
- Lucas Medino (UC Berkeley EECS, Visiting Researcher, 2019).
- Eli Bronstein (UC Berkeley EECS Undergraduate, 2019), Symbio Robotics.
- Nathan Blair (UC Berkeley EECS Undergraduate, 2018-2019).
- Jonathan Lee (UC Berkeley EECS Undergraduate, 2017-2018), PhD student at Stanford.
- Frank Jiang (UC Berkeley EECS Undergraduate, 2015-2016), PhD student at KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Sweden.

#### Invited Talks

#### Safe and Data-Efficient Learning for Robotics

Google Robotics Seminar, 2020.

## Scaling Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability Analysis for Robotics: Multi-agent Systems to Real-time Computation

Institute for Pure & Applied Mathematics (IPAM), 2020.

## Safe and Data-Efficient Learning for Robotics

Yale University, Department of Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science, 2020.

Georgia Tech University, School of Electrical and Computer Engineering, 2020.

Cornell University, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, 2020.

Cornell University, Department of Computer Science, 2020.

Harvard University, School of Engineering And Applied Sciences, 2020.

University of British Columbia, Department of Computer Science, 2020.

University of Southern California, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, 2020.

#### Safe Learning-Enabled Decision Making for Robotics in Novel Environments

ETH Zurich, Department of Mechanical and Process Engineering, 2019.

## Safe Learning-Enabled Decision Making for Autonomous Navigation in Novel Environments University of Toronto, UTIAS, 2019.

CITRIS/CPAR Control Theory and Automation Symposium, 2019.

Workshop on Algorithms and Architectures for Learning-in-the-loop Systems in Autonomous Flight, ICRA 2019.

## Combining Optimal Control and Learning for Visual Navigation in Novel Environments Simons Institute Annual Industry Day, 2019.

#### **Deep Learning Quadrotor Dynamics for Flight Control**

CITRIS-Honeywell Drones: Technology, Policy and Society Conference, 2018.

#### Overcoming Model Bias in Model-Based Learning

Berkeley Artificial Intelligence/ Berkeley Deep Drive Workshop, UC Berkeley, 2016.

#### Outreach

#### Girls in Engineering Camp

UC Berkeley, 2019

A week-long, non-residential summer camp for San Francisco Bay Area students entering 6th, 7th, and 8th grades to explore different aspects of what it means to be an engineer.

Inclusion@RSS RSS, 2019

Mentored several early career graduate students who belong to traditionally underrepresented groups in robotics.

#### **Berkeley School Volunteers**

Berkeley, 2017-2018

Volunteer teacher for middle school students in public schools.

### National Social Service Volunteer (Prayas Program)

IIT Kanpur, 2008-2012

Taught underrepresented and underprivileged K-12 students who could not afford quality education. I was awarded the **IIT Kanpur excellence award in community services** for my efforts.

#### PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

#### Visual Navigation Among Humans with Optimal Control as a Supervisor

Varun Tolani, *Somil Bansal*, Aleksandra Faust, Claire J. Tomlin arXiv Preprint, 2020 (under review)

# A Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability-Based Framework for Predicting and Analyzing Human Motion for Safe Planning

 $Somil\ Bansal,$  Andrea Bajcsy, Ellis Ratner, Anca D. Dragan, Claire J. Tomlin International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2020

## Generating Robust Supervision for Learning-Based Visual Navigation Using Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability

Anjian Li, *Somil Bansal*, Georgios Giovanis, Varun Tolani, Claire J. Tomlin, Mo Chen Conference on Learning for Dynamics and Control (L4DC), 2020

#### Combining Optimal Control and Learning for Visual Navigation in Novel Environments

Somil Bansal, Varun Tolani, Saurabh Gupta, Jitendra Malik, Claire J. Tomlin Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL), 2019

## An Efficient Reachability-Based Framework for Provably Safe Autonomous Navigation in Unknown Environments

Andrea Bajcsy, *Somil Bansal*, Eli Bronstein, Varun Tolani, Claire J. Tomlin *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, 2019

#### Reachability-Based Safety Guarantees Using Efficient Initializations

Sylvia Herbert, Somil Bansal, Shromona Ghosh, Claire J. Tomlin

IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2019

#### Closed-Loop Model Selection for Kernel-based Models Using Bayesian Optimization

Thomas Beckers, Somil Bansal, Claire J. Tomlin, Sandra Hirche IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2019

### A New Simulation Metric to Determine Safe Environments and Controllers for Systems with Unknown Dynamics

Shromona Ghosh, Somil Bansal, Alberto Sangiovanni-Vincentelli, Sanjit Seshia, Claire Tomlin ACM International Conference on Hybrid Systems: Computation and Control (HSCC), 2019

#### Goal-Driven Dynamics Learning via Bayesian Optimization

Somil Bansal, Roberto Calandra, Ted Xiao, Sergey Levine, Claire Tomlin IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2017

#### Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability: A Brief Overview and Recent Advances

Somil Bansal, Mo Chen, Sylvia Herbert, Claire Tomlin IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2017

#### FaSTrack: a Modular Framework for Fast and Guaranteed Safe Motion Planning

Sylvia Herbert, Mo Chen, Soojean Han, Somil Bansal, Jaime F. Fisac, Claire Tomlin IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2017

#### Safe Sequential Path Planning of Multi-Vehicle Systems Under Disturbances and Imperfect Information

Somil Bansal, Mo Chen, Jaime F. Fisac, Claire Tomlin American Control Conference (ACC), 2017

#### Learning Quadrotor Dynamics Using Neural Network for Flight Control

Somil Bansal, Anayo K. Akametalu, Frank Jiang, Forrest Laine, Claire Tomlin IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2016

#### Plug-and-Play Model Predictive Control for Electrical Vehicle Charging and Voltage Control in Smart Grids

Somil Bansal, Melanie Zeilinger, Claire Tomlin IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2014

Journal Publications

#### Provably Safe and Scalable Multi-Vehicle Trajectory Planning

Somil Bansal, Mo Chen, Ken Tanabe, Claire Tomlin

IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology (TCST) (under review)

## SPEC: An Approach to Determine Safe Environments and Controllers for Systems with **Unknown Dynamics**

Somil Bansal, Shromona Ghosh, Alberto Sangiovanni-Vincentelli, Sanjit Seshia, Claire Tomlin IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (TAC) (in prepration)

## FaSTrack: a Modular Framework for Real-Time Motion Planning and Guaranteed Safe **Tracking**

Mo Chen, Sylvia Herbert, Haimin Hu, Ye Pu, Jaime F. Fisac, Somil Bansal, SooJean Han, Claire Tomlin

IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (TAC), 2020

#### Robust Sequential Path Planning Under Disturbances and Adversarial Intruder

Mo Chen, Somil Bansal, Jaime F. Fisac, Claire Tomlin IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology (TCST), 2017

#### Decomposition of Reachable Sets and Tubes for a Class of Nonlinear Systems

Mo Chen, Sylvia Herbert, Mahesh Vashishtha, *Somil Bansal*, Claire Tomlin *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (TAC)*, 2017

## Plug-and-Play Model Predictive Control for Load Shaping and Voltage Control in Smart Grids

Caroline L. Floch, *Somil Bansal*, Claire Tomlin, Scott Moura, Melanie Zeilinger *IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid*, 2017

BOOK CHAPTERS

## Control and Safety of Autonomous Vehicles with Learning-Enabled Components

Somil Bansal, Claire Tomlin

Safe, Autonomous and Intelligent Vehicles, Springer, Page 57-75, 2019.

WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

## Combining Optimal Control and Learning for Visual Navigation in Novel Environments

 ${\bf Somil~Bansal}, \ {\bf Varun~Tolani}, \ {\bf Saurabh~Gupta}, \ {\bf Jitendra~Malik}, \ {\bf Claire~Tomlin} \\ {\bf Workshop~on~Deep~Learning~for~Visual~Navigation}$ 

Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2019

# Safe Learning-Enabled Decision Making for Autonomous Navigation in Novel Environments *Somil Bansal*, Claire Tomlin

Workshop on Algorithms and Architectures for Learning-in-the-loop Systems in Autonomous Flight International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2019

#### Advancing the Runtime of Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability Analysis

Somil Bansal, Claire Tomlin

Workshop on Towards Online Optimal Control of Dynamic Robots International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2019

TECHNICAL REPORTS

#### Context-Specific Validation of Data-Driven Models

 $Somil\ Bansal,$ Shromona Ghosh, Alberto Sangiovanni-Vincentelli, Sanjit Seshia, Claire Tomlin Technical report, March 2018

#### Safe and Resilient Multi-vehicle Trajectory Planning Under Adversarial Intruder

Somil Bansal, Mo Chen, Claire Tomlin Technical report, November 2017

### MBMF: Model-Based Priors for Model-Free Reinforcement Learning

 $\boldsymbol{Somil~Bansal},$ Roberto Calandra, Kurtland Chua, Sergey Levine, Claire Tomlin Technical report, June 2017